<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached July 17, 1681, at the assizes in Huntingdon before the Right Honourable the Lord Chief Baron Mountague and Mr. Justice Windham, judges of the assize / by Benjamin Smith, Rector of Boxworth, in Cambridge-shire.</title>
            <author>Smith, Benjamin, fl. 1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4021B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16974024</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16974024</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105575</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105575)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached July 17, 1681, at the assizes in Huntingdon before the Right Honourable the Lord Chief Baron Mountague and Mr. Justice Windham, judges of the assize / by Benjamin Smith, Rector of Boxworth, in Cambridge-shire.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Benjamin, fl. 1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: t.p. verso.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Jude I, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105575:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105575:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preached <hi>July</hi> 17. 1681. at the Aſſizes at Huntingdon, Before the RIGHT HONOURABLE, the Lord Chief Baron <hi>Mountague.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. JUSTICE <hi>WINDHAM,</hi> Judges of the Aſſize.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Benjamin Smith,</hi> Rector of <hi>Boxworth</hi> in <hi>Cambridge-Shire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Three Crowns</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel</hi> in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:105575:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 8. <hi>Line</hi> 6. <hi>for</hi> concern; <hi>Read</hi> concerns; <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> This is a dubious term. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>r.</hi> This <hi>f.</hi> Thus. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 33. <hi>r.</hi> the Saints, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. 2. To the Saints and faithful Brethren which are at <hi>Coloſſe. p.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 32. <hi>f.</hi> Qui <hi>r.</hi> Cui.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105575:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Jude, ver. 3.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was needful for me to write unto you, and Exhort you, that ye ſhould earneſtly Contend for the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are no Contentions any wayes ſo ſmart and ſevere as thoſe that are raiſed about Religion, and among thoſe, it is obſervable, that none are ſo inhumanely cruel, deſperately malicious, or unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally miſchievous, and ſpiteful, as thoſe that are raiſed againſt the true Religion, and the Profeſſours of it.</p>
            <p>For falſe Religions have no better defence or ſecurity to themſelves, than to perſecute the true; and if they could remove that out of the way, there would then be none to detect their Error, or Convict them of falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. As <hi>Herod</hi> burnt all the <hi>Genealogies</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that none might be left to ſhew that his Lineage was defective.</p>
            <p>Beſides, as the true Religion improves mens minds, and teacheth them not only true courage, and inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them with a greatneſs and generoſity of Spirit; but alſo makes men more gentle and kind, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth Charity and Love to our Neighbour to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent height: So on the other hand, all falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons one way or another, debauch the minds of men, and introduce the ſeeds of ſurlineſs, and pride; of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of others, and a diſdain to be oppoſed, and rivets in their minds a mercyleſs regard to thoſe that differ from them.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105575:3"/>
            <p> Hence it follows, that if power and opportunity fall in ſucceſsfully with thoſe Principles they embrace, that force and violence, and all the inhumane wayes of Compulſion are taken up as the proper and peculiar Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, either to defend and propagate their own Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, or to undermine the Articles and Practice of the contrary Religion. For that Religion that wants the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity and lovelineſs of Truth, to defend or promote it, and cannot by its own native vertue and beauty main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain its ground, and infinuate it ſelf into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> others, muſt neceſſarily have recourſe to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Methods of Force and Rage, of Bloodſhed an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that it may aw and ſcare men into a Compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſubdue the Timorous; and take thoſe out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe minds being endued with more generous Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, know not how to truckle and ſubmit to Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
            <p>Thus the Turk hath turned his Swords into Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhares, (but in a ſence far different from that Evangelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal promiſe) and prepares the Soyl, and plants his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by the point of the Sword, and the dint and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of Force and Violence. And from hence it was, that the Chriſtian Religion in all Ages found ſuch oppoſition both from <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Pagan,</hi> not by Reaſon and Arguments, but by Rage and Perſecutions, by Racks, and Geobits, by Fire and Faggot, and by all the Arts and means that malice and fury, that ſpight, and inhumane Cruelty could invent or deviſe; not to Convince, but to Ruine and Deſtroy men. Hence was that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſeries of thoſe dreadful Perſecutions, that raged ſo horribly againſt the Chriſtians, whileſt the Empire was in the hands of Pagan-Princes; they being hated, as our Saviour foretold, of all men for his <hi>Names ſake.</hi> And if any Famine or Mortality, or any Evil occurrent had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105575:3"/> the Empire, the common Cry was, <hi>Chriſtianos ad Leones;</hi> as if theſe had been the certain cauſe of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry common Calamity, or the Wrath of their Gods, could only be appeaſed by the Blood and Ruine of innocent men.</p>
            <p>But we need not go ſo far off, to make inſtances, nor ſearch the Annals of Heathen or Turkiſh ſtories, for a proof of what I ſay. The Fraud, and Force, the Spight and Cruelty, that <hi>Rome,</hi> Chriſtian-Rome hath alwayes perſecuted us with, abundantly ſhews with what Arts a falſe Religion is to be eſtabliſhed, and gives us as great an evidence, as any, that the Religion which they ſo propagate, is not from God.</p>
            <p>Hiſtorians tell us, that <hi>Romulus</hi> layed the foundation of thoſe Walls in the Blood of his Brother <hi>Remus,</hi> and the humour of it Cleaveth to thoſe walls ſtill; and though <hi>Rome</hi> be now called Chriſtian, ſhe ſtill goes on to Found her Walls, and eſtabliſh her dominion in the Blood of her Brethren. And though old <hi>Rome</hi> advanced her Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire over the world, by Sword and Slaughter, by a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Conqueſt, and the invaſion of other mens Rights, yet it was by Proweſs and Valour, and the Generous Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of an open War. And in this, indeed, <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Rome</hi> ſtill, that ſhe uſurps, and encroacheth, that ſhe battens in Blood, and thrives by Confuſion and Slaughter; but yet ſhe is much departed from the Generoſity, and Gallantry of old <hi>Rome,</hi> in that they ſcorned to proceed, but by open Defyance, and gave an Enemy warning to look to himſelf; but theſe thrive by Treachery and Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſteal upon us like a <hi>Thief in the night,</hi> and are aſhamed of no Arts, and baulk no Methods, how dirty, and indecent; how mean, or unmanly ſoever, that may but any wayes tend to promote their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and advance (as they call it) the Catholick cauſe.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105575:4"/>
            <p> Hence an inhumane Cruelty, where-ever they get an advantage, does conſtantly attend their Succeſſe, the certain ſigne of a cowardly and degenerous mind; of which the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſacre, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion, and their Butcheries in the valley of <hi>Peidmont,</hi> are laſting and undeniable Monuments. And all the advances they have made, and the ground they have gotten, hath moſt-what been, by Baſe and Treacherous Plots, by Fire, and Poiſon, and Daggers; wayes, that God, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Diſpute) never appointed his Church to riſe by, or to defend her ſelf with; and a Method of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Chriſtian Religion does utterly abhor and diſown.</p>
            <p>And all theſe, and more too, we have by experience found to be practiſed by them upon our ſelves, in this Nation. If not all in Effect, no thanks to them who laid their Traines, and did their utmoſt; yet all this they have endeavoured to do, and would certainly have done, if the infinite mercy and good Providence of God had not been our defence to their confuſion. It was out of this Shop, that all thoſe Treacherous and Trayterous attempts againſt the Life of that excellent Princeſs of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bleſſed Memory, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> firſt proceeded; From <hi>Rome</hi> they derived both their encouragement, and firſt formation. From hence <hi>Lopez</hi> was ſet on to Poiſon her, <hi>Parry, Sommervile,</hi> and others, to Stab her. A Practice that Heathen-Rome ſcorned to uſe, or own; but <hi>Rome</hi> called Chriſtian, makes theſe the chiefeſt of her Arts, and relyes on them as her moſt ſucceſſeful, and appoſite Methods of vanquiſhing Princes. From <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armado received an encouragement, and the Apoſtolical Benediction, and from the ſame ſource ſprang that Plot of the <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon;</hi> a deſigne which none but <hi>Rome</hi> could Foſter, and which none but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105575:4"/> thoſe who had put off all ſenſe of Religion, Mercy or Humanity, could ever invent or approve of; and which the Savage inhabitants of the coldeſt Climes would be ſtartled at, and tremble to hear of. From the ſame place, our late dreadful confuſions were high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fomented: and that Sacred, and Royal Blood which ſo much ſullied the honour of our Religion, and ſtill Cryes ſo loud for Vengeance, was not ſhed without their Concurrence, and Aſſiſtance; the miſchievous and buſie Jeſuite, being ſo wicked as to promote the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, and ſo impudent, as to Boaſt of it when it was done.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould I mention former things, ſince of late they have given us the Compendium, and Abſtract of all their villanies, in that horrid and execrable Plot, which is yet on foot; and which, in deſpight of all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, and oppoſition that can be made, they have the face and inſolence ſtill to puſh forward, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, with the utmoſt of a reſtleſs, and implacable vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and malice. A deſigne ſo horrid and ghaſtly in its Aſpect, ſo contrary to all true ſentiments of Piety, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and Allegiance, that I do not wonder that they uſe all their Arts, either to ſtifle its <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> or to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the <hi>Odium</hi> of it from themſelves upon others. And yet it is ſo ſuitable to their former Methods, and ſo well adapted to ſerve and promote the ends of a falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that we have no cauſe to queſtion who are its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, nor any reaſon to think they will give over its Purſuit, ſo long as the fainteſt hopes remain that it may take effect.</p>
            <p>But this oppoſition againſt the true Religion, ſhould make the Profeſſors of it the more watchful and reſolute in its defence, that the endeavours of the enemy to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Truth, and Eclipſe the light of the Goſpel
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105575:5"/> may meet with a ſuitable reſiſtance in the wiſdom and vigilance of the Defenders of it, and theſe laſt efforts of their languiſhing cauſe be baffled. If <hi>Rome</hi> ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeks to corrupt the <hi>Faith,</hi> and by any Methods to impoſe a falſe a Religion upon us; it is reaſonable, and fair, that we oppoſe their Intrigues, by all juſt wayes, and according to Saint <hi>Judes</hi> exhortation here, <hi>Earneſtly contend for the Faith, which was once delivered to the Saints.</hi> An Exhortation, which if it was uſeful in his dayes, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be needleſs now in ours: And ſince the Laws are the Barriers and juſt defence of our Religion, as well as our Liberty; and the true Faith is the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of every man; it cannot be unſeaſonable, nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper, at this time, when both Magiſtrates and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are met to enquire into the importance and obligation of the words of Saint <hi>Jude,</hi> and to ſee what he meant by it; and how far we are concerned in it, when he ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was needful for me to write unto you, and Exhort you, that ye ſhould earneſtly contend for the Faith, which was once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words contain</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subject and Theam of his Epiſtle what he wrote about; and that is, to Exhort you, <hi>That ye ſhould earneſtly contend for the Faith, which was once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The reaſon why he choſe this ſubject, and wrote about this matter: <hi>It was needful for me to write unto you.</hi> It was requiſite and needful to manage that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and the Fourth Verſe gives a ſufficient account of the neceſſity of it: <hi>For there are certain men crept in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, who were before of old ordained to this Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ungodly men, turning the Grace of our God into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciviouſneſs, and denying the only Lord God, and our Lord</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105575:5"/> 
               <hi>Jeſus Christ.</hi> There were ſome crept in, that began to ſubvert the <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Sap,</hi> the very foundations of it; Saint <hi>Jude</hi> therefore thought it needfull for him to give them notice and warning of it, the <hi>Faith</hi> was in danger; he therefore Exhorts them to <hi>contend earneſtly</hi> for it. For this is the Office of the Seers, to ſtand and obſerve, and give notice of the approaching danger, that the flock may not be ſurprized by any ſuddain invaſion, nor ſeduced by the fly inſinuations of thoſe that lye in <hi>wait to deceive,</hi> and <hi>creep in unawares.</hi> This was the danger the Church then was in and which it hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince been freed entirely from; this gave occaſion to Saint <hi>Jude</hi> to manage this ſubject then, and makes it ſtill fit for the Miniſters of the Goſpel to preſs and urge: And to exhort you, <hi>That ye ſhould earneſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where there are theſe Two Things to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What it is they were to <hi>Contend</hi> for; and that is, <hi>The Faith once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. How they were to contend for it; and that is, <hi>Earneſtly.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>1. What they were to <hi>contend</hi> for<hi>—The Faith,</hi> &amp;c. This certainly is a ſubject well worthy of the Apoſtles greateſt, and moſt vigorous <hi>Exhortations,</hi> and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers moſt earneſt <hi>Contentions.</hi> This is that we ſhould moſt earneſtly ſeek after; and having obtained it, they moſt diligently endeavour to retain. It is that Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pledge of his Love, which the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, our dear Redeemer, delivered us to keep; and that, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had endured all the indignities and contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affronts, and ſuffered the worſt of things that men could inflict, and ſhed his Blood to ſeal and confirm
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105575:6"/> it to us. Nay, this is that in which our eternal life conſiſts, and the only way that our Saviour hath layed down for us to go to Heaven in. This is that which Saint <hi>Jude</hi> calls here in the beginning of this verſe <hi>[the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſalvation,]</hi> that Method and way of Salvation, that was delivered for all alike, and alike concern; all to know, to obſerve, and to walk in. Which, what it is, will more fully yet appear, by conſidering the words which the Apoſtle here deſcribes it by <hi>(viz.) The Faith once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where it is expreſſed,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By its name, the <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. By a conſiderable diſtinguiſhing Circumſtance, <hi>once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>1. By its name, the <hi>Faith.</hi> This a Dubious term in it ſelf, as being capable of a different application; and ſignifieth ſometimes one thing, and ſometimes another. But the moſt uſual diſtinction, and which is fully ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for my preſent purpoſe, is that diviſion of Faith, <hi>In Fidem quâ Credimus,</hi> and <hi>Fidem quam Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There is the <hi>Fides quô Credimus,</hi> the <hi>Faith</hi> by which we believe; and this is no more than the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal aſſent and conſent of the mind, to the Doctrines of the Goſpel, and the Revelations of God, which when it hath that influence upon the Soul, as to captivate it into a due ſubjection and obedience to the Laws of God, and the Rules and Precepts of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is that which is by Divines, called a <hi>ſaving and juſtifying Faith;</hi> a Faith that works by love, and is the fulfilling of the Goſpel-condition; a Faith that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives and ſubmits to the Lord Jeſus in all his Offices, and as he is offered in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>This is an uſual and frequent meaning of the word
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105575:6"/> 
               <hi>Faith</hi> in the New-Teſtament; and that which we ſhould, by all means, <hi>Contend</hi> and endeavour to preſerve entire. That neither the pleaſures of this life, nor the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a Corrupt mind; neither the ſly inſinuations of lewd Companions, nor the intereſt and Grandeur of this preſent World, divert us from it. That neither to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the Luſts of the Fleſh, nor to form or promote an Intrigue or deſign, we ſhould violate the Rules of a good conſcience, or make bold with the Laws of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> In ſhort, that neither Debauchery, nor Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, nor Knavery, ſhould make us forget our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Goſpel, or in any thing depart from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of that Religion which we profeſs. This is a <hi>Faith</hi> thus to be <hi>Contended for</hi> and preſerved; but this is not the <hi>Faith</hi> here meant in the Text. For beſides this, there is</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Fides quam Credimus.</hi> And by that is meant the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> And the Doctrines of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and his Apoſtles; the Meſſage they brought, the Rules they gave, the Means they preſcribed in order to eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are very frequently in Scripture called the <hi>Faith.</hi> This <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 7. <hi>And the word of God increaſed</hi> (or got ground) <hi>and the number of the diſciples multiplyed in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem greatly, and a great company of the Prieſts were obedient to the Faith.</hi> So Galat. 1. 23. <hi>He that perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us in times paſt, now preacheth the Faith, which once he destroyed.</hi> And ſo again 1 Tim. 3. 9. <hi>Holding the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Faith in a pure conſcience.</hi> And to name no more, ſo it is in this place, <hi>That ye ſhould earneſtly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the Faith once delivered to the Saints.</hi> Where it is not the <hi>Faith</hi> whereby they believe, but the Faith which they believe, <hi>the Faith delivered to the Saints</hi> to be believed, received and kept, that is meant. Not an <hi>Aſſent</hi> to the Revelation, but the <hi>Revelation</hi> it ſelf
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105575:7"/> to which we give Aſſent. The <hi>Faith</hi> here then is the Truth, the Goſpel of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines of Salvation, and thoſe Rules and Means that guide us to eternal life; or in one word, the True Religion.</p>
            <p>And this is further ſet out,</p>
            <p>2. By a conſiderable diſtinguiſhing Circumſtance, <hi>once delivered to the Saints.</hi> Every Doctrine is not to be <hi>Contended for,</hi> and every Religion is not worth the keeping; and every thing that hath by men, been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to men, is not too tenaciouſly to be adhered to. The <hi>Faith,</hi> the Religion which Saint <hi>Jude</hi> propoſeth to our Care, and endeavours to keep, is deſcribed by this, which diſtinguiſheth it from all that are falſe, and ſets the true, and currant ſtamp upon it, it is the <hi>Faith,</hi> the Doctrine, the Religion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this being the <hi>Mark,</hi> and diſtinguiſhing Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> which we muſt <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for,</hi> it muſt the more carefully be enquired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that we may not miſs our Mark, and <hi>Contend for</hi> what we ought to avoid. There are therefore two things to be explained in theſe words, and we muſt enquire who are the Saints, and what is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Text.</p>
            <p>1. Who are the <hi>Saints</hi> here, to whom the <hi>Faith</hi> was delivered? And here I think the Anſwer is plain, and eaſy enough, that by Saints he means, no other than thoſe, to whom the Goſpel was firſt preached, and who did receive it and believe. <hi>[Sanctos</hi> (ſays one) <hi>uſitato Scripturae modo vocat Credentes; he calls the Believers Saints according to the uſual Language of the Scriptures.]</hi> And thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls the Believers, and Embracers of the Goſpel, the <hi>Saints</hi> and faithful brethren which are at <hi>Coloſſe;</hi> and <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>To all the Saints in</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105575:7"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt Jeſus that are at</hi> Philippi.</p>
            <p>But then conſidering that it is Saint <hi>Jude</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of our Lord that writes thus, as is evident by the firſt verſe of this Epiſtle, where he ſtyles himſelf [Jude, <hi>the ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt and brother of</hi> James,] and by the Inſcription of the Epiſtle, which though it be not Canonical Scripture, yet is the ſenſe of the Ancient Church, which entituleth it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Epiſtle of Jude the Apostle.</hi> This Epiſtle then being writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by him, and calling the Doctrine of the Goſpel, the <hi>Faith delivered to the Saints;</hi> that which in his time was delivered and received, was preached and believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</p>
            <p>To us it ſets the Mark and ſtamp of Antiquity, upon that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which he calls upon us to <hi>Contend for.</hi> And if we ask what is the Doctrine we ought to receive, what the <hi>Faith</hi> we ought to <hi>Contend for?</hi> the Anſwer is in Saint <hi>Jude;</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles preached, and the <hi>Faith</hi> the Ancient and Eldeſt Chriſtians received. This directly oppoſeth all <hi>Novel</hi> Doctrines, and all Religions that are late and upſtart. Whatſoever is not derived from theſe Ancient, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt Fountains, we are no ways obliged to maintain or <hi>Contend for,</hi> as being none of the <hi>Faith delivered to the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet this is the quarrel between the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and us. She hath notoriouſly and viſibly corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Faith,</hi> and departed in numerous inſtances, from the true and old Religion; We deſire to adhere to it, and to ſeparate the Precious from the Vile, and in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> our ſelves, have done no more, than returned to what was truely Ancient, and have onely recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the Rubbiſh of their Novel, Superſtitious, and Idolatrous Doctrines, the <hi>Faith that was once delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105575:8"/> 
               <hi>to the Saints.</hi> For this they Charge our Doctrines with Novelty, and call our <hi>Faith</hi> a New Religion; but to whom that Charge moſt juſtly belongs, will be no hard matter to the impartial and unbiaſſed mind to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> wittily derides the <hi>Arrians,</hi> that when they produced their Confeſſion of <hi>Faith</hi> in the Council of <hi>Rimini,</hi> they ſet down in the ſtile of it the Day, and the Month, and the Conſulls when it was made, as from thence dating the Beginning of their <hi>Faith,</hi> and fixing the firſt Original of their Hereſy, and ſhewing thereby that their <hi>Faith</hi> was Late, and upſtart. But what would he have ſaid to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> had he lived now? And how ſmartly would he have rebuked their Novel Encroachments? the Body of whoſe Religion, as it is now embraced, bears date from the Counſel of <hi>Trent;</hi> and there is not one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle in their <hi>Faith,</hi> wherein they differ from us, but we can ſhew, and prove it, to be of a late foundation: Late (I mean) in compariſon with the Truth, and the <hi>Faith that was once delivered to the Saints.</hi> What Chriſt, and his Apoſtles preached, and what the firſt and eldeſt Chriſtians believed, and received, we own and adhere to; but other things that are not found among theſe Doctrines, or are repugnant to them, we juſtly renounce as New and Erroneous; though they have contracted a venerable Ruſt by their Age, and ſeek to impoſe upon us under the mask of Antiquity, and by the deſcent, and length of their Pedigree. <hi>Primum quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que veriſſimum,</hi> is <hi>Tertullians</hi> Rule; and we deſire to ſtand and be tryed by it, and would have nothing impoſed upon us, that the Scriptures (the true and <hi>Authentick</hi> Records of Antiquity) do not mention, nor own. The Doctrines which the Apoſtles preached, the Rules of Life and Salvation which they gave, is what we <hi>Contend</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105575:8"/> 
               <hi>for;</hi> for this is the <hi>Faith delivered to the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now conſider,</p>
            <p>2. What is to be underſtood by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Once delivered</hi> in the Text. There are two Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes given of it by Interpreters; both which may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in, as being both indeed implyed in the word.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Once</hi> may carry the ſenſe of <hi>Conjunctim,</hi> and ſo the learned and judicious <hi>Hammond</hi> paraphraſeth it <hi>[preached uniformly to all by the conſent of all the Apostles.]</hi> This was that Doctrine that was One and the ſame, though preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by different perſons; this the Apoſtles all agreed in, and obſerved in their preaching through the world; that though they were ſo far diſtant one from another, yet they all preached the ſame thing, and made no Difference in the Doctrine they Preached, in the <hi>Faith they delivered to the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How happy had it been for the World, and how much had it conduced to the peace and Purity of the Church, and to the ſafety and ſecurity of the Souls of men, if the Miſſionaries of <hi>Rome</hi> had obſerved and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by the ſame Rule, and kept to the <hi>Doctrine that was once delivered,</hi> and had taught none other things, then what the Apoſtles by Common conſent, and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of mind, had preached.</p>
            <p>Then had they never impoſed ſo much Falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine upon the world, nor ever preached things ſo vaſtly different, from the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Then might the Church, in a great meaſure, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained her Virgin-Purity ſtill, and had not been defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, nor the world been diſturbed by the inſolent En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then might <hi>Images</hi> (a very Fornication in Religion,) have kept their place among the Batts and Moles, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105575:9"/> in holes and Brambles, where the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſayes, the <note place="margin">Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Jews,</hi> upon their Reformation, ſhould throw theirs; and had never crept forth to ſee the light, to be adorned and admired, nay, to be ſet up and worſhipped by Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men.</p>
            <p>Then might the Church have been left to pray and ſay, <hi>Amen,</hi> with underſtanding, and to go to the Throne of Grace, in a way where all knew what they were doing; and the Scriptures, thoſe Fountains of living waters, had never been ſealed up under an unknown Tongue, from the eyes and uſe of thoſe, whoſe Duty as well as Intereſt it is, to peruſe and underſtand them.</p>
            <p>Then might the Church have enjoyed the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> as they were firſt inſtituted for her uſe, and as our Lord appointed they ſhould be received; and the <hi>Cup</hi> had neither been taken away, nor the <hi>Bread</hi> been made a God, and a Prodigious Idol to be worſhipped, and eaten. Had they followed the <hi>Faith</hi> and Doctrine of the Apoſtles, they would never have dared to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what our Saviour had Ordered, nor have preſumed to deprive the People of the <hi>Cup,</hi> when our Saviour at the firſt inſtitution of that Ordinance, ſaid, <hi>Drink ye all of it.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Then might Princes have enjoyed their Rights, and neither have been queſtioned nor moleſted in their Thrones, by thoſe who ought to be ſubject to them; and then might the People have led their lives under them, <hi>peaceably in all godlineſs and honeſty,</hi> and had never felt the effects of thoſe Fire-brands, which the <hi>Pope</hi> hath thrown abroad in the world; nor ever been taught to rebell againſt God and the King.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, then had that Maſs of Corrupt, Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Idolatrous Doctrines, that have with ſo much
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105575:9"/> confidence been broached, ſo highly to the diſhonour of Religion, and to the danger of Souls, never ſeen the light, nor defiled the Church; had they kept to the <hi>Faith that was once delivered,</hi> that is delivered <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctly</hi> by all the Apoſtles one and the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Once delivered,</hi> carries in it the ſenſe of <hi>Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably. Once for all,</hi> as we ſay, not to be changed or altered any more. God gave his people the <hi>Jews</hi> a Law, and Ordinances, of his own appointment; but theſe were not to hold, but till the <hi>Fulneſs of time was come,</hi> and then that diſpenſation was to ceaſe, and be done away, to make room for one more perfect and laſting; one to be ſo <hi>Once delivered,</hi> as not to be delivered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in another way, or with any addition, or amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And in this ſenſe the Scriptures, uſe the word elſewhere, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 35. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Once have I ſworn in my Holineſs, that I will not lye unto David.</hi> That is, certainly, immutably, and without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration. And this way both <hi>Grotius,</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> go. <hi>[Semel; Quia de ea Doctrina nihil ſit imutandum.</hi> Once, <hi>Becauſe nothing was to be changed in that doctrine.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore every Subſtraction, or Addition to this <hi>Faith,</hi> thus <hi>Once delivered,</hi> is a notorious Wrong to it; a Corruption of the Doctrine, and an Encroachment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Authority of God Almighty, in whoſe power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone it is, to make and eſtabliſh an Article of <hi>Faith.</hi> And therefore do we appeal to the Doctrine of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and deſire to ſtand, and be tryed by that; for ſince it was <hi>Once delivered</hi> ſo, as not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> having made both Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to it, and Variations from it, ſtands juſtly charged with that Novelty, which ſhe would fix upon us. When our <hi>Saviour</hi> reproves the corrupt Practices, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105575:10"/> Gloſſes of the <hi>Jews,</hi> he reduceth them to the true and Ancient ſtandard, and tells them, <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> And upon many of the Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we may write the ſame Remark, and ſhew, that <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We can tell by what ſteps the <hi>Papal Grandeur</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and by what unjuſt Encroachments and undecent huffs and inſolencies, they enlarged their dominions, and enſlaved the Church, and imperiouſly trampled upon Princes. We can tell them the Time, and prove it when they pleaſe, that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were more tractable and humble, and that the world did not take them to be ſuch uncontroulable Pieces, as afterwards they grew up to be. <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> ownes the Emperour <hi>Mauritius,</hi> for his Lord and Maſter, and declares him to be the Forerunner of <hi>Anti-christ,</hi> that deſires the Title of <hi>Oecumenical Paſtor,</hi> or univerſal Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. And he held the Chair in the end of the Sixth Century. But the world is much altered with them ſince, as to both theſe points; and now they aſſume a power of depoſing Princes, and to diſpoſe of the Kingdomes of the earth at their pleaſure. Now, it is an Article of their <hi>Faith,</hi> that the <hi>Pope</hi> is Head of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Church. A thing that was not thought to be <hi>ſo from the beginning.</hi> For Saint <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in his Expoſition of that place, <hi>[Rom.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> ſays, <hi>that the Apoſtle en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes this to all, both to</hi> Prieſts, <hi>and</hi> Monks, <hi>and not to Lawmen only,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Although thou be an Apoſtle, although thou be an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, although thou be a Prophet, or whatſoever elſe thou art.]</hi> And for the other Point the Council of <hi>Calcedon</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, that the See of Conſtantinople <hi>ſhould have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Conc. calced. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>equal priviledges with old</hi> Rome,] which they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105575:10"/> never had done, had the <hi>Pope</hi> then been thought the Supream Head of the Church, and Chriſt's onely Vicar upon earth.</p>
            <p>Again, we can tell them, when the Worſhip of <hi>Images</hi> was firſt Authorized in their Church, and it is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly known, that the Second Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> was the firſt that determined for it, and that was paſt the middle of the Eighth Century.</p>
            <p>Their Prodigious Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> (the peculiar Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome)</hi> was firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh, but not compleatly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, nor the Name brought in till <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, in his <hi>Lateran</hi> Council in the year 1215. A thing ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unknown to all the Fathers of the eight firſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turyes, and a Name ſo ſtrange and unuſual, that a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>French</hi> Antiquary obſerves, that no Antient Dictiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Spon M. S.</hi>
               </note> either Greek or Latine, hath the word, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſo much as contains, or expreſſeth the Senſe of it, not in two ſo Copious Languages.</p>
            <p>And ſo for their gainful Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> it's evident that the Primitive Times, as well as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are ignorant of it, and utterly ſtrangers to it. And it's ſomewhat a puzling Queſtion, that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Antiquary asks <hi>Le Cheſe,</hi> (this preſent <hi>French</hi> King's Confeſſour) that if the Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory</hi> be Ancient, and not of a late Coinage and Date, why in all the Ancient <hi>Epitaphs</hi> before the ſeventh or eighth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, we never meet with an <hi>Orate pro anima,</hi> or a <hi>Requieſcat</hi> in them? And yet now no Roman <hi>Epitaph</hi> is made without them.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Half Communion,</hi> its well enough known, was firſt determined in the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and they had the face to do it, with an <hi>non obſtante</hi> to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours own Inſtitution, and to the Practice of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105575:11"/> Church. And though they grant, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> adminiſtred it to his Diſciples in <hi>Both Kinds,</hi> and in the primitive Church the Faithful uſed to partake of it ſo; yet <hi>ad evitandum aliqua pericula, &amp; ſcandala,</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſome imaginary Dangers and Scandals, they would venture to determine contrary to the Practice of the Church, and the Inſtitution of Chriſt. And this bold Council ſate not, till the Beginning of the Fifteenth Century.</p>
            <p>And ſo (would my Time and your Patience ſerve) I could eaſily go over all the Articles in difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us; and either tell you the Time, when they were firſt introduced, and the Council that gave them Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; or prove, that there was a Time long before them, when the contrary Practice was in uſe, and when the Doctrines which we <hi>Contend for,</hi> in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to theirs, were received and embraced.</p>
            <p>Is this then the <hi>Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> that neither the Scriptures nor Antiquity knew any thing of? Is this the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which is ſo lately crept forth, and that in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to what they delivered on Record in Scriptures? Theſe muſt therefore needs be the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a Prodigious Inſolence, for Men to take upon them to add to, or alter what God hath eſtabliſhed, and firſt Themſelves to depart from that <hi>Faith, which was once</hi> (that is, immutably and unalterably) <hi>delivered to the Saints,</hi> and then to require Others, under pain of Damnation, to go along with them.</p>
            <p>No Church or Society of men upon earth, either hath or can have ſufficient Authority or power, to Coin new Articles of <hi>Faith,</hi> and give them a ſacred Stamp, and make them Obligatory to the Conſciences of men. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Church hath a ſufficient Power in matters of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105575:11"/> Diſcipline for her own Government, and can make Laws, and Cannons relating to Decency and Order, which the Members of that Church are bound to <hi>Obey, not onely for Wrath, but Conſcience ſake:</hi> and for this we need not go to <hi>Rome,</hi> nor are we bound to ſtand to her Determinations; we have all the juſt Rights, and Power of a Church, within our ſelves; and what have we to do with <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Rome</hi> with us? But to add more Articles of <hi>Faith</hi> to the Apoſtles Creed, and to require thoſe to be believed, and received with the ſame <hi>Faith,</hi> and Aſſent of mind, that the others are (as <hi>Pope Pius</hi> the Fifth, falſly ſo call'd, hath impiouſly done) it is an intollerable Encroachment upon the Authority of the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and a wide Deviation from that Doctrine <hi>once delivered to the Saints,</hi> and ſo delivered, as not to be altered.</p>
            <p>For this is the <hi>Faith,</hi> that we are concerned in, and the onely <hi>Faith</hi> that we are to <hi>Contend for;</hi> that which was <hi>delivered to the Saints,</hi> that which was preached by the Apoſtles, and believed and embraced by the Saints, thoſe ancient and eldeſt Chriſtians. What is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this we ought to reject, and for this we ought to <hi>Contend;</hi> that we may retain, and preſerve intire and pure, the True Religion, the truly Ancient, Catholick, and Apoſtolick <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this for the Firſt thing, <hi>What we muſt Contend for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The Second thing in the words to be enquired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, is, <hi>How this Faith muſt be Contended for?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is worthy our moſt ſerious Enquiry. For the <hi>Faith</hi> we muſt <hi>Contend for,</hi> being a matter of ſo great Concern, the Manner of our <hi>Contending for</hi> it, is of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Conſideration alſo; for if we <hi>Contend</hi> not as we ought, or otherwiſe than we ought, we may loſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105575:12"/> what we ſtrive for, inſtead of obtaining it; for it hath been known, that ſome have ſo <hi>Contended for</hi> the <hi>Faith,</hi> and by ſuch Ways and Means, as have been a real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to it; and they have either loſt their Religion, or ſhewed that they had None, while they <hi>Contended for</hi> it, by unjuſt and irreligious Ways. And this indeed as much as any thing proves, that the Religion which the Church of <hi>Rome Contends for,</hi> and would impoſe upon the world, is none of the <hi>Faith, Once delivered to the Saints;</hi> in that ſhe uſeth ſuch irreligious, and unconſcionable Methods, to impoſe and Crow'd it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us by. 'Tis fit for the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran</hi> to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented upon the point of the Sword, and falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have need of external Force and Violence, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce and ſettle them in the world; but this is ſo contrary to the Progreſs and Proceedings of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and the Ways of its Advancement, that this alone is a Diſparagement to any Religion, that it needs ſuch Arts and Methods to eſtabliſh it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Apoſtles went about doing good,</hi> and convinced the world, of the <hi>Truth</hi> of what they ſaid, by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Reaſon, and the evidence of Miracles from above. But if any were ſo Obſtinate, as to reſiſt the Evidence by which they ſpake, and would not give heed to the Truth they delivered, they <hi>ſhook off the duſt of their feet, as a witneſs against them,</hi> and left them (as a juſt puniſhment of their Obſtinacy) to periſh in their Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; but we never read, that they Cut their Throats, or fired that houſe or City, that would not receive them.</p>
            <p>When they were in their State of Infancy (as to their <hi>Faith)</hi> and did no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> underſtand Themſelves, nor the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that <hi>Faith</hi> and Religion, they were afterwards to preach, they were once indeed for fetching Fire
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105575:12"/> from Heaven, to conſume the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> that would not receive their Maſter; but then they would not have made the Fireballs themſelves, but have uſed onely, what God would have ſent them from Heaven. But how ſharply does our Saviour repreſs their blind, and ignorant Zeal? <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. 55, 56. <hi>But he turned, and rebuked them, and ſaid, ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of; for the Son of Man is not come to Deſtroy mens lives, but to Save them.</hi> But now how Contrary muſt that Religion be to that, which they preached, and our Saviour ordained, which requires ſo contrary Methods to introduce, and advance it. <hi>Rome</hi> ſays, <hi>Come to us,</hi> for <hi>Salvation is onely with us,</hi> and its neceſſary in order to it, to be Subject to us, and to Believe, and receive all that we tell you; but if we refuſe, (as it is fit we ſhould do) till we ſee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Reaſon (for Saint <hi>John</hi> bids us <hi>not to believe every</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. chap. 4. v. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Spirit, but to try the Spirits)</hi> they inſtead of convincing us by Reaſon or Scripture, or any other ſufficient Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will daſh out our Braines, and fire our Towns; and thus <hi>Contend for</hi> the <hi>Faith,</hi> and plant their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not by the Bible but the Sword, and uſe all the ways of <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Violence and Cruelty, to ſubdue us to their Opinions, and make us believe.</p>
            <p>Surely theſe are not of the temper of the <hi>Holy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> who was Meek and Merciful, however they may call themſelves by his Name; and undoubtedly that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion can be none of his, which inſpireth the minds of thoſe who profeſs it, with ſo much barbarous and bloody Cruelty. Can that Religion be true, which muſt be ſettled and propagated by Violence and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief? and is that the Goſpel which makes its Entrance, by a direct Violation of all the Rules of Equity, Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty or Humanity? Is this the Religion of the <hi>Holy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:105575:13"/> which proceeds and advanceth it ſelf, by a direct Contradiction to his Practice, and a perfect Violation of all his Laws and Precepts? And is this the Way of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, for men to do all that, for which God himſelf hath told us, we ſhall be damned? Is Murder, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is Sedition and Rebellion, any ways conſiſtent with the Sentiments of a true Piety? Or is this a Religion of God's Appointment? Undoubtedly theſe things make it manifeſt, that ſuch a Religion is not from God, nor is the Spirit by which ſuch men Act, either guided or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by him.</p>
            <p>The True Religion, and the <hi>Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> teacheth us, to be Meek and Merciful, and to endeavour the Good of all men. To reclaim our Brother from the Error of his way, by Patience, Long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and Doctrine: To bear with him, and inſtruct him, and not to daſh out his Braines, if we cannot Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute him. It teacheth us to be Juſt and Honeſt, Sober and Peaceable, Obedient and Submiſſive to the higher Powers, and not to Lye, nor Equivocate, nor to break the Bands of humane Society, nor to diſturb the Peace and Government of Kingdoms, and to confound the world. That Religion muſt not be good, that muſt be thus advanced, and therefore I ſaid, that it being our duty to <hi>Contend for</hi> the <hi>Faith,</hi> it is conſiderable, How we muſt <hi>Contend for</hi> it, leſt we ſhould think it Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to <hi>Contend</hi> in ſuch a way, as the true <hi>Faith</hi> will not endure, to be maintained and defended by; and ſo ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loſe, or at leaſt diſparage our Religion, inſtead of preſerving, and honouring the <hi>Faith,</hi> by our undue and irregular Contentions for it.</p>
            <p>And to Anſwer this, it muſt be conſidered, that Saint <hi>Jude</hi> writes to men, that were in no place of Authority in the State; For as the Chriſtian Religion was already
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105575:13"/> under Perſecution, and hated by <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> ſo were the Profeſſours of it, of no Eſteem then in the world; there was no Chriſtian Magiſtrate who bare the Sword, nay the Sword was in the hand of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Religion, and the Magiſtrates were thoſe who oppoſed and perſecuted the True Religion. So that it cannot be ſuppoſed, that the Apoſtle can here mean by this <hi>Contending for</hi> the <hi>Faith,</hi> any oppoſing force with Force, or a <hi>drawing the Sword for the defence of the Goſpel;</hi> for he writes to thoſe who had nothing to do with the Sword, and exhorts thoſe who were <hi>Subjects</hi> and not <hi>Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For we may aſſure ourſelves, that thoſe who preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and wrote, by the Inſpiration of the ſame Spirit, could not contradict one another; and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> having both expreſly commanded a <hi>Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1, 2. 1 Pet. 2. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>to the Supream Magistrates and Powers,</hi> and thoſe very Powers being at that time Enemies to the Goſpel, and Perſecutors of the true Religion, whom (for all that) they command ſo expreſs a Subjection to; it cannot be ſuppoſed, that Saint <hi>Jude,</hi> any more than they, could think Religion a juſt pretence for Rebellion; or when he bids the Chriſtians <hi>Contend for</hi> the <hi>Faith,</hi> could mean by it, an Oppoſition to the Rulers and Governours, that God had ſet over them.</p>
            <p>And the conſtant Practice of the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which in this Caſe is the beſt Interpreter of Saint <hi>Judes</hi> Exhortation, evidently ſhews, that they did not thus underſtand it. They loved and prized the <hi>Faith,</hi> more than their lives, and chearfully ſuffered, and dyed for the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> but they never rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Rebellion for the Defence of their <hi>Faith,</hi> or diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the State, or oppoſed the Government, for its Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement. No Hiſtory, either <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Christian,</hi> gives
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105575:14"/> any the leaſt Hints, of any Sedition they raiſed, or any the leaſt Oppoſition they made to the Civil Governours, in all the time of the <hi>Pagan</hi> Emperours; even when the Perſecutions raged with the greateſt Heat againſt them, and they were Tortured and killed with the greateſt Barbarity and Inhumanity, onely for being Chriſtians. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his <hi>Apology for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> to the Emperour <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi> and <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> in his to the Emperour <hi>Severus,</hi> both mention the peaceable, and quiet Deportment of the Chriſtians un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Government, which had been too weakly (not to ſay impudently) done, if the Chriſtians had been guilty of diſturbing the State, by Sedition and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Nor was all this a <hi>Patience per force;</hi> their Numbers were neither ſo ſmall, nor their Courage ſo low, but they might have created Diſturbance enough, had they thought it Lawful ſo to proceed. <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells the Emperor <hi>Severus</hi> in that excellent Apology he preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, in the behalf of the Chriſtians, that their Numbers and Courage were ſufficient, to have ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Defence, and to make their Party good againſt their Enemies, if they thought it Lawful ſo to do. <hi>[S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> enim hoſtes apertos, &amp; non tantum vindices occultos agere vellemus, deeſſet nobis vis Numerorum, &amp; Copiarum, &amp;c. For if we had a mind to proceed by open Hoſtility, could we want either Numbers, or Forces ſufficient? we are but of yeſterday, and yet we fill all Places, your</hi> Cities, Iſlands, Caſtles, Corporations, Councils; <hi>your very</hi> Camps, <hi>and</hi> Tribes, <hi>and</hi> Companies; <hi>your</hi> Palace, Senate, <hi>and</hi> Courts <hi>of</hi> Juſtice: <hi>Sola vobis Templa relinquimus, onely your Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are free from us. Qui Bello non Idonei,</hi> &amp;c? <hi>For what War ſhould we be unfit or unprepared, though our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were inſerior, who ſo willingly lay down our lives, if</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105575:14"/> 
               <hi>in our Religion, it were not more Lawful to be killed than to kill.]</hi> Nay, he ſays, that without a Rebellion they could Ruin their Perſecutors, only by with-drawing from them; and if ſo great a number of men, ſhould retire into ſome remote Corner of the World, their very Receſs would be a puniſhment to them. <hi>[Proculàubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſetis ad Solitudinem veſtram, ad ſilentium re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, et Stuporem quendam quaſi mortuae Urbis; Doubtleſs</hi> (ſays he) <hi>you would be astoniſhed, at the Solitude we ſhould leave you in, at the ſilence and ſtillneſs of your City, as if it had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired at our departure.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Chriſtian Fortitude in thoſe days, ran in a ſtream quite contrary to Violence and Reſiſtance; and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Advantages of ſuffering for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, were then thought to be ſo great, that no dread of Death, nor probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Prevailing, could tempt them to ſuch a Courſe. And of this we have an eminent Inſtance in the <hi>Thebean</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Grot. de jure Bell.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 4.</note> Legion, which conſiſted of ſix thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty ſix men (all Chriſtians) who in the Reign of <hi>Maximian</hi> laid down their Arms, and were every man cut off and Martyred, rather then they would ſacrifice to Idols at the Emperours Command.</p>
            <p>And when the Empire was now turned Chriſtian, and their Numbers mightily encreaſed, when all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Employments, and all places of Truſt were happily lodged in Chriſtians hands: <hi>Julian</hi> comes to the Throne, a profeſſed <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> one that renounces the <hi>Faith</hi> he had early imbibed, and openly declares for <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> and ſets up their horrid Rites, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition again; and yet no man oppoſeth him by Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Armes, no Sedition, nor Mutiny is raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, though the ſtrength of the Empire was then in Chriſtian hands.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105575:15"/>
            <p> Prayers and Tears to <hi>GOD,</hi> and earneſt Entreaties, and humble Apologies to the Emperours, were the Ways and Methods, of the Defence of the <hi>Faith,</hi> in Ancient times; and till the <hi>Popes</hi> had debauched the Minds of men, and for their own Intereſt, taught them to deſpiſe the ſecular Power, we never heard of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion raiſed in the world, upon the account of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor of the Defence of the <hi>Faith,</hi> by Force and Arms. This is a way which the Religion of the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> abhors, and this is not the way, that Saint <hi>Jude</hi> here <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts,</hi> us to <hi>Contend for the Faith</hi> in.</p>
            <p>For though he uſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which does undoubtedly refer to thoſe Exerciſes, which were ſo famous, and ſo much in uſe among the <hi>Grecians,</hi> and are called by them the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, conſiſting of thoſe manly Exerciſes of <hi>running, wrestling,</hi> and <hi>Combating;</hi> yet it is as evident, that in the uſe of the word, he does not refer to the Force and external Violence, uſed in thoſe Cames; but to the Diligence, Induſtry, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Sufferance of the Combatants. Thus it's plain Saint <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth the word, to ſignify the <hi>Patience,</hi> and <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 4. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtancy</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> in their ſpiritual Race and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, in their ſufferings and endurance of Labour and Perſecution; and thus our Saviour applyes it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 24. And I believe it will no where be found in the New Teſtament, to ſignify the <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> or <hi>Contention,</hi> of external Force and Violence.</p>
            <p>Not but that I think it Lawful for the Magiſtrate, to draw the Sword in defence of the True Religion. <hi>For he is the Miniſter of God—and beareth not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the Sword in vain.</hi> If the <hi>Pope,</hi> as he hath formerly done, ſhould give away this Kingdom to him that can catch it, or ſet any Prince a work (as he loves to do) to force us into a Subjection to him; no doubt the King
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105575:15"/> may Lawfully oppoſe Force with Force, and defend his Kingdom from every Invaſion; God hath put the Sword into his hand, to manage for the Defence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as well as of the People. But then this is the Caſe of the Magiſtrate, whoſe the Sword is, and makes nothing to thoſe, who have none of that Power com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them. To theſe the Practice of our Saviour, who refuſed to be reſcued by Saint <hi>Peter's</hi> Sword, and the Command he gave with the Reaſon of it, Mat. 26. 52. <hi>Put up again thy Sword into its place; for all they that take the Sword, ſhall periſh by the Sword:</hi> is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient direction and Rule, what they have to do, and ſhews them how dangerous, and unlawful it is to be meddling.</p>
            <p>How then muſt we <hi>Contend for the Faith?</hi> Surely in the head of all our Endeavours, our <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> ought firſt to be placed, as the Ancient Arms of the Primitive Church, and thoſe moſt ſucceſſefull Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, with which they Encountred the Rage of the Enemy, and by which their <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Conſtancy</hi> tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed in the end. Our <hi>Faith</hi> is from God; and to whom therefore ſhould we go for its Defence, but to him who can with eaſe defeat the Deſignes of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and infatuate the Counſels of their beſt Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance; who as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Fruſtrateth the tokens</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 44. v. 25.</note> 
               <hi>of the Lyars, and maketh Diviners mad, that turneth wiſe men backwards, and maketh their knowledge fooliſh.</hi> If he be among us, we need not fear all the Efforts of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Hell;</hi> but if he forſake us, our Defence is gone, and our <hi>Glory departed,</hi> and <hi>Ichabod</hi> may be written up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all our pleaſant places.</p>
            <p>But other Means are to be added to theſe alſo. And every one in his ſeveral Sphere, muſt employ the Talent that God hath given him; for God loves not the Lazy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105575:16"/> Suppliant, nor will hear the Deſires of thoſe, that will always lye ſtill and Cry, <hi>God help.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> muſt <hi>Contend</hi> in his Sphere, for the Defence of the Church, as well as the Government of the State; the Preſervation of the true Religion, as well as the Peace, is within the exerciſe of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and ought to be part of his Care: He <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends</hi> for it by a tenderneſs and Care over all its Concerns, and by Reſtraints upon the Petulancy and Unrulineſs of men, who would either Corrupt the Doctrine, or diſturb and interrupt the Peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>And here is alſo Your Sphere to Act <hi>(my moſt Honourable Lords)</hi> to whoſe Wiſdom and Skill the Execution of thoſe Laws are Committed, by which our Religion hath hitherto been defended, and ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily flouriſhed. I Shall not preſume to direct, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, or <hi>Exhort</hi> you; the Knowledge we have of Your Love to Religion, and of your Faithfulneſs in Your Truſt, will not ſuffer us to fear, that You will be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, in the Defence of that Religion, which you Love ſo well; or let thoſe Laws which are ſo great a part of Your Truſt, be baffled or buried, on which the Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Peace, and Security of our <hi>Faith,</hi> at this time, ſo much depends.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minister</hi> muſt Act in his Sphere; and he <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends for the Faith,</hi> by declaring the mind of God in Truth, and expounding ſincerely the Oracles of <hi>GOD.</hi> By oppoſing and convincing Gain-ſayers, and defending the Truth from <hi>Hereſy</hi> and <hi>Error,</hi> and the Sophiſtical Tricks of thoſe, <hi>who lye in wait to deceive,</hi> and as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Lead Captive Silly women, laden with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>All men</hi> (as Chriſtians) muſt <hi>Contend</hi> in a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105575:16"/> way, ſuitable to them as ſuch, by Knowledge and Practice, by Love and Sufferings, and all the Methods that are Proper and Lawfull, and ſuit with Chriſtians, conſidered as ſuch, in their private Sphere and Capacity. And to theſe in this Circumſtance it is, that Saint <hi>Jude</hi> directs his Exhortation, and perſwades them to <hi>Contend for the Faith.</hi> That is, exhorts them to an earneſt, and immutable Adherence to it, ſo as not to forgo it, for all that the Enemy can do. Neither to be ſcared out of it by Dread <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Danger, by Violence or Death; nor to be cheated and wheadled out of it, by the Inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe that lye <hi>in wait to deceive,</hi> and <hi>[Creep in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares]</hi> that deprave the <hi>Faith,</hi> and corrupt the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Goſpel, and <hi>[turn the grace of God into Laſciviouſneſs]</hi> or exchange the Truth of God, for a Lye. And thus to ſecure our ſtanding in the <hi>Faith,</hi> and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that Religion, and Purity of Doctrine, that God hath bleſſed us with, no Ways are more Suitable and Proper, or likely to be more Succeſsfull, than theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To understand well, and be throughly informed, in the Principles and Fundamentals of that Religion, which we profeſs.</hi> For the greateſt, and moſt ſucceſsfull Conqueſts, that in any age the Enemy hath obtained, have ever been upon thoſe that are weak, and <hi>Unstable in the Faith:</hi> the Wavering mind hangs trembling, in an equal Suſpence between Truth and Falſhood, and theſe hardly eſcape the Aſſaults, or ſtand the Shock of thoſe, who lye in <hi>wait to deceive.</hi> And therefore the Methods of the Enemy have uſually been, to pick out thoſe to ſubvert, whom they ſee <hi>Ignorant and Unſtable;</hi> as knowing theſe to be the moſt liable, and likely to be brought to their Lure. And indeed, how ſhould it be otherwiſe; for they that are not well informed, in what they profeſs, may eaſily enough be perſwaded, that their Profeſſion is Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105575:17"/> and the Beſt Religion may Eaſily be diſparaged to them, that do not underſtand its Nature, and have not enquired far enough into it, to diſcern the <hi>Beauty and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And doubtleſs, this hath given the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> a vaſt Advantage againſt us; who know well enough how to improve it, in that ſo many are ſtrangers, to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of that Religion, which they profeſs, as having ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been Inſtructed in them, nor taken the pains to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, what it is they pretend to believe. Too many have ſatisfied themſelves, with being of that Profeſſion, in which they were born and brought up, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the trouble, to underſtand what that Profeſſion is, or to have any other Argument for it, than their Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And therefore, when I reflect upon that Ignorance in Religion, that is growing up, and that little Concern or Regard, that men have to be well verſed, or informed in the Fundamentals of it; inſtead of wondring, that <hi>Rome</hi> hath gained ſo many from us, I onely wonder that they have gained no more. And I very much fear, that if the time ſhould ever come, that men might with Safety, or advantage, change the Church of <hi>England</hi> for that of <hi>Rome;</hi> there are too many, that would need but little Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and all becauſe they ſo little Know the Truth, the Beauty and Excellency of that Religion, which now they profeſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To Practiſe ſeriouſly and Conſcientiouſly, what we profeſs.</hi> To hold the True <hi>Faith</hi> in Notion, and to deny it in Practice, is to pull down with One hand, what we erect with the Other; and to ſubvert and betray the <hi>Faith,</hi> that we ſeem to <hi>Contend for.</hi> And indeed, it is not eaſy to ſuppoſe, that a man ſhould be reſolute to Suffer for any Religion, nor ſtand any ways Vigorouſly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105575:17"/> in the Defence of it, who will not ſubmit to the Power of it, nor will let his Life be regulated, nor his Luſts be mortified by it. To the Profane perſon, all Religions are alike; and that which bids faireſt for his Intereſt, or is moſt ſuitable to his Inclinations, Carries it with him. It is the Practice of Religion that renders it Truely ſweet, and pleaſant to the Profeſſours of it; and none but thoſe, can heartily love the <hi>Faith,</hi> and be Zealouſly concerned for its Defence, that have Experienced the Power and Influences of it, in themſelves.</p>
            <p>To Practiſe therefore what we profeſs, is a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble means of Defence, for the Religion we own; for this engageth God on our ſide, and lets the Enemy ſee, it is in vain to Tamper, or be meddling. For to live up to the Principles of our Profeſſion, and to adorne our Religion with a ſuitable Converſation, is to <hi>bring forth Fruit,</hi> and to <hi>glorify GOD;</hi> and where theſe are found, the End is anſwered, for which the Goſpel is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed; and ſo long the <hi>Candlestick</hi> ſhall not be remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, while People rejoyce, and walk in the Light. And therefore it is obſervable, that the Removal of the <hi>Means</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and an Eclipſing the Light of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> hath ever in all places been preceded by a Decay of <hi>Piety,</hi> and an Inundation of <hi>Profaneſs.</hi> This pulls down the Wrath of <hi>GOD,</hi> and that makes the Cunning, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of men effectual; God will walk no more among them, that walk contrary to him; and they that will Practiſe no Religion, may eaſily enough be perverted to Any, how irrational or abſurd ſoever it be. God grant, that that Coldneſs, Looſeneſs, and Profaneſs, that ſo univerſally over-ſpreads this Nation, be not too ſad a Prognoſtick, and preparatory to the Departure of the Goſpel from among us. For this our Saviour Threatens the <hi>Jew,</hi> Matth. 21. v. 43. <hi>Therefore I ſay unto you, the</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105575:18"/> 
               <hi>Kingdom of God ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all be taken from you, and given to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bringing forth the fruits thereof.</hi> Our Provocations are too like theirs; God grant our Puniſhment be not the ſame too!</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A Christi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n love, and Union among our ſelves:</hi> This is an excellent Means of defence of the <hi>Faith,</hi> and a pertinent and prevalent Method of <hi>Contending</hi> for it. By this we ſecure our ſelves from all Aſſaults without; and while Love compacts and cements the Body, it makes it impregnable to all the fruitleſs Attempts of the Enemy. Our Unity would be our Strength, as well as as our Beauty; and if our Adverſaries could not Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate a Party, and form Diviſions among us, they would ſit down in Diſpair of ever prevailing, and would be leſs frequent and brisk in their Attacks.</p>
            <p>But while we Bite and Devour one another; while we Rage, and Raile at, and mutually Subvert, and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine each other; whilſt fierce Debates, and Unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Cenſures, and Spight, and Malice, and Wrath do ſwell the Spleen, and Exaſperate the Minds of men one againſt another; we reproach our Religion by an unſuitable Deportment, and expoſe our ſelves an eaſy Prey, to the Cunning and Malice of our Enemies. For the Goſpel we <hi>Contend for,</hi> is a <hi>Goſpel of Peace;</hi> and the God we ſerve, is the <hi>God of Peace;</hi> and the Badge of Chriſt's Diſciples, is to <hi>love one another.</hi> If then to Contradict the Deſign of the Goſpel, be the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way to haſten its departure, in vain do men pretend a zeal of Religion, in Bitterneſs and Animoſity; or give out, they <hi>Contend for the Faith,</hi> while they violate the Laws of Chriſtian Charity, and Caſt away the bands of Concord, Love and Union. It is much to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, leſt God in his juſt Indignation at theſe things, ſhould let in the Common Enemy among us, and Cure the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105575:18"/> Rancor, &amp; take off the edge of our ſpirits, and teach us more Kindneſs, &amp; a more tender regard one for another, by invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us all in the ſame common Calamity, and judgment.</p>
            <p>I Am ſure nothing more weakens our ſtrength, nor more roundly, or ſucceſsfully advanceth the Projects of the Enemy, than our fierce and unmerciful Conteſts one with Another. We pull down our Defence with our own hands, and our ſelves ſap, and undermine thoſe Walls, and Foundations, which they ſo much deſire to ſee Levelled with the ground. Hence it is, that <hi>Rome</hi> hath always been induſtrious, and vigilant to Create, and foment Diviſions among us; for theſe preſent them with thoſe advantages againſt us, which all their own Proweſſe, or Policy could never have procured for them: But a Chriſtian Love, and firm Union among our ſelves, would be no leſs their Terror, then their Confuſion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>To ſuffer reſolutely the worſt that man can inſlict, rather than forgo our</hi> Profeſſion, <hi>or deny the</hi> Faith. This is that manner of Contention, which I conceive the Apoſtle Chiefly aimes at in the Text, by the uſe of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as I have already intimated; and this is that Way in which every particular perſon may for himſelf, and in his own Sphere victoriouſly <hi>Contend.</hi> This will render all the Attempts of men in vain, and whether they Fawn or Rage, a mind reſolved to endure the utmoſt, rather than forgo the <hi>Faith,</hi> will weather the ſtorm, and ſtand the ſhock, and come off Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant in the end. For the Rage, and violence of men, may bind the Hands, or force the Body; but the mind is free, and no Compulſions can debauch the Conſcience. They Can reach this Temporal life, &amp; tear the heart out of the Body; but the Soul is beyond their reach, and can never tear the Love of Chriſt, and his Truth, out of the Heart that is not willing to part with it.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:105575:19"/>
            <p> When therefore all other means of <hi>Contending for the Faith,</hi> either fail, or are uſeleſs, through the Anger of <hi>GOD,</hi> or the Perverſeneſs of Men, the good Chriſtian in his particular Sphere may <hi>Contend for</hi> it, and be ſure to preſerve, and keep it entire and inviolate, by <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Conſtancy,</hi> and a mind prepared to ſuffer, whatever the Rage, or Malice of Men can inflict. For he that Can expoſe his Fortune to the Rapaciouſneſs of Men, his Body to the Tormentor, and his Life to the death, need not fear what man can do, but may be ſure to preſerve his Conſcience pure, and his <hi>Faith</hi> ſound unto the end.</p>
            <p>And though Fleſh and Blood may Recoile, and fancy this Method leaſt of any; yet the Chriſtian is ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with the greateſt reaſon that Can be, to encourage him to it. This is the <hi>Path</hi> that our Saviour trod before us, and through Tribulation and Sufferings, the Captain of our Salvation was made Perfect. <hi>He endured the Croſs deſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 2.</note> 
               <hi>of the Throne of God.</hi> This way thoſe great and famous Worthies in the Goſpel, thoſe <hi>Primi Pilares Fidei noſtrae,</hi> the Ringleaders of our <hi>Faith,</hi> ſtood up for the <hi>Faith,</hi> and Sealed it with their deareſt Blood, <hi>[and they loved not their lives unto the death.]</hi> And to the ſame Engagements <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 11.</note> our Saviour encourageth us, and bids his Diſciples, <hi>[fear not them which kill the Body, but are not able to kill the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Soul.]</hi> And the Apoſtle propoſeth the example of our Maſters Sufferings, as the ſupport of our <hi>Faith,</hi> and Courage in the greateſt Tryals. <hi>[For conſider him</hi> (ſays Saint <hi>Paul) that endured ſuch Contradiction of ſinners againſt himſelf, lest ye be weary and faint in your minds.]</hi> This the <note place="margin">Heb. 12 3</note> thing we <hi>Contend for,</hi> deſerveth at our hands, for the <hi>Faith</hi> is Precious, and the Teſtimony of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, out-weighs the Terrors of death, and the Love of God is better than life it ſelf: And this by our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105575:19"/> with God, we engage our ſelves to; and we Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Chriſt's Diſciples upon Termes ſhort of theſe. He that loves his Life more then Chriſt, is unworthy to be a a Diſciple of Chriſt; and he that for Fear denyes the <hi>Faith,</hi> denyes Chriſt the Lord and Founder of it. And though our Maſter does not always Call his ſervants to Heaven, in a Fiery Charriot, and in Tribulation, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; yet he expects that they ſhould all of them be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready, and reſolved to go that way if he calls them; and he will receive none that decline that way when he calls them by it. For he hath ſaid <hi>[if any man come to me, and hate not his Father, and Mother, and Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 14. 26. 27</note> 
               <hi>and Brethren, and Siſters, yea, and his own life alſo, he cannot be my Diſciple; and whoſoever doth not bear his Croſs, and come after me cannot be my Diſciple.]</hi> Let us then ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dread loſing the <hi>Faith,</hi> than our <hi>Lives;</hi> and rather fear being diſcarded by our great Maſter, turned out of his Service, or diſowned by him, then to be vexed and worried, and killed by men. If God calls us to ſuffer, let us not think <hi>[strange at the Fiery Tryal]</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> calls <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 12.</note> it; but with Patience, and Courage obey the Call, and with a firm Mind, and undaunted Reſolution, hazzard our lives, to ſave our Souls; &amp; quit the World, to preſerve the <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Enemy is at hand, &amp; lodged under our very Walls; what God may permit, we know not; what they would do, is now ſufficiently diſcovered and demonſtrated to every one, that is not of the Party, or willing to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon. Tis time to think ſeriouſly of our Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to fortify our minds with Courage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy againſt the impending Evil. 'Tis time that our Breaches were Healed, and our Contentions among our ſelves were Baniſhed, that we might all unite in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Defence; and all Combine (as one man) to <hi>Contend earneſtly for the</hi> Faith <hi>which was once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
